OK.
Here's a question for you.
How many of the people
you write for are psychic
with infallible memories?
It's a dumb question,
right?
And yet, it's so,
so easy to treat them as if they are.
We see it all the time.
Take this sentence.
'Owing to the fact that
we have been experiencing
severe difficulties with our suppliers,
coupled with industrial action
by postal staff,
we are sorry to inform you
that your order has been delayed.'
Let's leave aside the fact
that this is a very long sentence –
33 words long in fact.
No.
We're talking about
the structure here.
There are two parts
to this sentence.
What's happening:
the order has been delayed
and we are sorry.
And why it's happening:
supplier difficulties,
industrial action.
And the writer has put the why first.
Now, OK,
they may have been thinking
they'd get their excuses in early,
but it also does two other things,
which are bad news for engagement and building
understanding.
First,
it keeps the reader guessing.
They have to read
three-quarters of the sentence
before they get to the point,
the what.
When you write
a sentence like that,
you're asking the reader
to invest their time and energy,
to set aside whatever
else they're doing,
and just keep reading,
taking it on trust that it will be worth
it.
OK, if you were
building up to telling them
they'd won the lottery
or even got a job they'd applied for,
then you can be pretty sure they'd
be happy to keep reading.
But for most situations,
you're more likely to just end up
annoying them.
And you're also
doing something else
when you write sentences like this:
you're asking the reader
to remember that first part
of the sentence, the why,
while they read the last part.
And then you're asking them
to recall the first part
and tack it on to the end.
That's a lot to ask. Really.
It's a big drain on
what could be a tired, stressed,
or busy reader.
Because, yes,
hey're just like you.
Scientists call it cognitive load,
the amount of brain work
needed to understand something.
The higher the cognitive load,
the harder
your reader has to work.
Wouldn't it be better
to let them save their brainpower
for retaining what you've said
or thinking about how they'll
apply the information?
The main part of a sentence
is what's actually happening.
Why is secondary.
Really, it's easy.
Just write the first part first
and the second part second,
and you'll make it easy
on the readers and easy on you.